<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-12-04T02:15:24+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>website
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">lessons learnt from the spacecraft simulators</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/sc-sim/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="lessons learnt from the spacecraft simulators" /><published>2025-05-19T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-19T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/sc-sim</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/sc-sim/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, several friends who have started their own companies or labs at various universities have asked me to share some “lessons learned” from our work on spacecraft simulators.</p>

<p>For context, I was a core member of the spacecraft simulator team at Caltech during the early years of my PhD. I led over 100 live demonstrations and contributed to research featured in the following papers presented in the <a href="#references">References</a> section.</p>

<p>First, what is a spacecraft simulator? It is a facility consisting of a flat floor with spacecraft hovering above it to simulate the lack of friction in space. See the video below for a demonstration.</p>

<p><a href="https://youtu.be/z5mIcnEnws4?si=q8bnn10yEbuJ-isF"><img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/z5mIcnEnws4/0.jpg" alt="Spacecraft Simulator Demonstration" /></a></p>

<p>Here’s a list of lessons I’ve learnt from the spacecraft simulators (order is random):</p>

<p>Table of Contents:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#availability-of-a-compressor">Availability of a compressor</a></li>
  <li><a href="#floor-repairability">Floor Repairability</a></li>
  <li><a href="#strict-cleaning-procedure">Strict Cleaning Procedure</a></li>
  <li><a href="#air-bearing-design-and-floating-height">Air-Bearing Design and Floating Height</a></li>
  <li><a href="#safety-and-pressure-systems">Safety and Pressure Systems</a></li>
  <li><a href="#spacecraft-simulator-air-system-inspection">Spacecraft Simulator Air System Inspection</a></li>
  <li><a href="#onboard-compressor-efficiency">Onboard Compressor Efficiency</a></li>
  <li><a href="#isolate-air-sources-on-the-spacecraft-simulator-for-air-flow">Isolate Air Sources on the Spacecraft Simulator for Air Flow</a></li>
  <li><a href="#hire-high-pressure-experts">Hire High-Pressure Experts</a></li>
  <li><a href="#floor-material-choice">Floor Material Choice</a></li>
  <li><a href="#floor-cleaning-tools">Floor Cleaning Tools</a></li>
  <li><a href="#references">References</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="availability-of-a-compressor">Availability of a compressor</h3>

<p>Ensure access to a reliable compressor or gas refill system. For example, having an on-site compressor streamlines testing compared to relying on external tanks that require frequent swapping or delivery delays.</p>

<h3 id="floor-repairability">Floor Repairability</h3>

<p>This is important.
Test the floor’s resilience and repair process together with the installer. Intentionally scratch or dent a sample area and verify that it can be restored quickly and cost-effectively. A floor that is easy to repair allows you to run more aggressive experiments, knowing that accidental damage can be fixed without major disruption or cost.</p>

<h3 id="strict-cleaning-procedure">Strict Cleaning Procedure</h3>

<p>Establish a clear, enforceable cleaning protocol. Dust, sweat, shoe residue, and debris can degrade performance, increase friction, and tarnish the floor’s finish.
You can schedule deep cleaning at regular intervals, although we haven’t done this. Ensure cleaning supplies are always available. We used
isopropyl alcohol and a microfiber cloth to clean the floor.</p>

<h3 id="be-careful-what-the-air-in-the-spacecraft-simulator-room-is-connected-too">Be careful what the <strong>air</strong> in the spacecraft simulator room is connected too.</h3>

<p>Check the room’s air supply. 
If the simulator room shares air circuits with other facilities or the external environment, insects, dust, or contaminants can enter and disrupt experiments. Consider maintaining positive pressure with filtered air and isolating critical air lines with backflow preventers.
It happened to us that bugs got into the room. This was a pain to clean.</p>

<h3 id="residue-from-socks-and-sweat">Residue from Socks and Sweat</h3>

<p>Be aware that users walking in socks can leave behind sweat and residue, which dulls the floor over time.</p>

<h3 id="air-bearing-design-and-floating-height">Air-Bearing Design and Floating Height</h3>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2025-05-19/puck.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="mounts" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div style="text-align: center;">
(Source: Newway Air Bearings)
</div>

<p>Carefully design and test the air-bearing puck geometry and the target floating height for your simulator’s payloads. 
The vendors provide plots of the floating height vs the air pressure. 
Here’s a picture of the pucks we used.</p>

<h3 id="safety-and-pressure-systems">Safety and Pressure Systems</h3>

<p>Be strict about safety. Those things are pressurized so they be unsafe. The high pressure tubes need to be mounted well. Here’s a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZywM18-l-74">video</a> of a failed pressure system and a watermelon. These things can be deadly, if not handled properly.</p>

<h3 id="spacecraft-simulator-air-system-inspection">Spacecraft Simulator Air System Inspection</h3>

<p>Define a regular maintenance schedule for all pressurized systems. Unexpected leaks can cause sudden system failure, especially before a demo.</p>

<h3 id="onboard-compressor-efficiency">Onboard Compressor Efficiency</h3>

<p>During my time at Caltech, I invented an on-board compressor system that was running continuously and helped maintain the pressure without needing to refill the tanks on-board the spacecraft simulator.
I used really basic materials, but it worked. I think a similar device could be built and will be more efficient than constant refilling.</p>

<h3 id="isolate-air-sources-on-the-spacecraft-simulator-for-air-flow">Isolate Air Sources on the Spacecraft Simulator for Air Flow</h3>

<p>Our spacecraft simulator has tanks at the top and at the bottom. The bottom tanks are in charge of supplying air to the air-bearing pucks. The top tanks are in charge of supplying air to the thrusters. 
Separate the air lines for these 2 regions to ensure constant flow.</p>

<h3 id="hire-high-pressure-experts">Hire High-Pressure Experts</h3>

<p>Consult or employ qualified high-pressure system specialists. They can assist with system design, ensure regulatory compliance, verify installation quality, and train operators.</p>

<h1 id="references">References</h1>

<p>[1]R. Foust, <strong>E.S. Lupu</strong>, Y.K. Nakka, S.J. Chung, F.Y. Hadaegh, “Autonomous in-orbit satellite assembly from a modular heterogeneous swarm”, Acta Astronautica 2020</p>

<p>[2] K. Matsuka, <strong>E.S. Lupu</strong>, Y.K. Nakka, R. Foust, S.J. Chung, F. Hadægh, “Distributed multi-target relative pose estimation for cooperative spacecraft swarm”, International Workshop on Satellite Constellations and Formation Flying (IWSCFF) 2019</p>

<p>[3] R. Foust, <strong>E.S. Lupu</strong>, Y.K. Nakka, S.J. Chung, F.Y. Hadaegh, “Ultra-soft electromagnetic docking with applications to in-orbit assembly”, 69th International Astronautical Congress, Bremen, Germany</p>

<p>[4] Y.K. Nakka, R. Foust, <strong>E.S. Lupu</strong>, D.B. Elliott, I.S. Crowell, S.J. Chung, F.Y. Hadaegh, “A Six Degree-of-Freedom Spacecraft Dynamics Simulator for Formation Control Research”, AAS/AIAA Astrodynamics Specialist Conference</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="robotics" /><category term="electrical_engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[lessons learnt from the spacecraft simulators]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Predicting the future</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/predicting_the_future/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Predicting the future" /><published>2025-02-27T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/predicting_the_future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/predicting_the_future/"><![CDATA[<p>In this article, I’ll talk about some multi-agent ideas that fascinate me.
I hope you find them interesting as well and maybe one day, someone will pick up on these ideas and make them a reality.</p>

<p>Let’s talk about the possibility of predicting the future by modelling the influence of each person’s decisions on the world.</p>

<p>👻 Fun fact: As a child, my summers at my grandparents’ house included a post-lunch tradition.
We’d gather around the table for Turkish coffee, brewed in the traditional style that left a thick layer of grounds at the bottom of each cup. 
After finishing our drinks, my grandmother, a chemist and food engineer with a whimsical side, would pretend to read our fortunes from the coffee grounds.
It was all in good fun; we knew she was making up stories, but her tales were always optimistic, filled with bright futures.
Her fascination with the mystical was a playful contrast to her scientific background—much like how my generation turns to puppies on Instagram for entertainment, her generation embraced the mystical for their fun.</p>

<p>I’ve been fascinated by the possibility of using a tool to predict the future.
Instead of relying on something whimsical like my grandmother’s coffee grounds,
what if we harnessed the power of AI?
Of course, I’m not suggesting that we analyze coffee grounds with a segmentation model—that would be far-fetched.
But imagine if we could model the cumulative impact of individual decisions on a global scale.
Could we potentially forecast future events and trends?</p>

<h2 id="1-how-do-the-decisions-from-one-person-influence-the-outcomes-of-another-person">1. How do the decisions from one person influence the outcomes of another person?</h2>

<p>Let’s consider an example to illustrate the potential of AI in predicting and preventing adverse scenarios:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Imagine two individuals, Person A and Person B.
Person A decides to drive after consuming alcohol one evening,
while Person B plans to visit In-N-Out for a burger.
Unfortunately, due to Person A's impaired driving, an accident occurs,
and Person B becomes involved because their path intersects with Person A's.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This situation could potentially be mitigated with the help of AI.
For instance, an AI system could analyze factors such as Person A’s alcohol consumption and the timing of their decision to drive, and it could warn them of the high risk of causing an accident, advising against driving.
Simultaneously, the AI could alert Person B about the increased risk of accidents along their route to In-N-Out, suggesting they delay their trip or choose a different destination.</p>

<p>This concept is related to the AI’s ability to simulate multiple future scenarios
based on real-time data, evaluating the outcomes of various decisions to provide timely warnings.</p>

<p>However, implementing such a system raises significant privacy concerns.
It would require continuous access to personal data and decision-making insights, a prospect that might be more palatable in a future where technologies like Neuralink have normalized the integration of AI in daily decision-making.
While this could dramatically enhance safety and decision-making efficiency, it also opens up a complex debate about privacy, autonomy, and the extent to which we are willing to allow AI to influence our lives.</p>

<h2 id="2-voting-and-future-of-the-world">2. Voting and future of the world.</h2>

<p>The process of voting has always captivated me,
particularly how it seems we make such significant decisions—like choosing a representative—with relatively little information. So silly!
While the media aims to inform us, their coverage can often be biased or even exacerbate misunderstandings.
Additionally, voters come from diverse educational backgrounds and are influenced by various social factors such as friends and family.</p>

<p>Consider how frequently political candidates make campaign promises,
only to pursue markedly different agendas once in office.
This discrepancy between promises and actions leads to a possibility: what if we could use AI to predict the likely outcomes of a candidate’s tenure based on their past decisions, historical data, and broader national history?</p>

<p>Imagine an AI-driven outcome tree for each candidate.
This model could predict, for instance, a 20 percent chance that a candidate might initiate a conflict, or a 30 percent likelihood of raising taxes.
Such predictions could empower voters to make more informed decisions, choosing candidates not just based on promises but on probable outcomes.</p>

<p>We always say: history repeats itself. 
Given that history often shows patterns of repetition, leveraging this data to predict future political actions seems both logical and feasible.
Modeling such a system would involve complex algorithms capable of analyzing vast datasets to identify trends and predict future events.
This would undoubtedly be a challenging yet fascinating problem to tackle, potentially revolutionizing how we approach voting and political analysis.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="future_ideas" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Predicting the future with AI]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review Book “Lessons from the Lobster. Eve Marder’s Work in Neuroscience”</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/books_lobster/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review Book “Lessons from the Lobster. Eve Marder’s Work in Neuroscience”" /><published>2025-01-19T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-19T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/books_lobster</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2025/books_lobster/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="review-of-the-book-lessons-from-the-lobster-eve-marders-work-in-neuroscience">Review of the book “Lessons from the Lobster. Eve Marder’s Work in Neuroscience”</h2>

<p>I recently finished reading “Lessons from the Lobster”, a book recommended by a student after my lecture on reinforcement learning and intelligence.</p>

<p>The book provides a detailed description of Eve Marder’s work in neuroscience, from her childhood to her current role as a professor at Brandeis University.
As a roboticist with almost no background in neuroscience, I found the book a bit difficult to follow when complex biology details were presented, so I skipped those parts and focused on the general ideas and lessons that I could apply to my work.</p>

<p>Marder’s research focuses on the neural circuits in the stomatogastric ganglion (STG) of lobsters, a small but remarkably flexible neural network consisting of just 30 neurons. 
This simplicity makes the STG a great model for studying neural circuits.
What’s interesting from the book is that even if there are only a few neurons, by doing neuromodulation, the STG can fire very differently. So such a small circuit is very flexible and can generate a wide range of behaviors.</p>

<p>I would recommend the book to anyone interested in neuroscience, biology, or even robotics, as it provides a great example of how to study a complex system by focusing on a small part of it. Maybe one day I’ll learn more about biology and neuroscience and I’ll be able to understand the book in more detail.</p>

<p>Off-topic, I am actually allergic to lobsters. 🦞</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><category term="AI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Review Book "Lessons from the Lobster"]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">partial file staging</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/git/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="partial file staging" /><published>2024-12-23T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-23T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/git</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/git/"><![CDATA[<p>Writing good commit messages is very important when developing a large project. It helps you and your team understand the changes you’ve made and why you made them.
Oftentimes, as PhD students, we tend to work alone and not care that much about the commit messages. However, when you start working with a team, you’ll realize how important it is to write good commit messages and to stage your files properly.
To me, setting up good practices and good workflows from the beginning is really important.</p>

<p>One command I really like is</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>git add -p
</code></pre></div></div>

<h3 id="what-is-git-add--p">What is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git add -p</code>?</h3>

<p>This command initiates an interactive staging session that allows you to selectively stage portions of a file.
This is particularly useful when you’ve made changes to a file and want to commit only some of those changes.</p>

<h3 id="how-to-use-git-add--p">How to use <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git add -p</code>?</h3>

<p>It’s really easy. Just type</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>git add -p
</code></pre></div></div>
<p>and then git will present you with a series of options.</p>

<p>For example, some that I use a lot are:</p>
<ul>
  <li>‘y’ to stage this hunk</li>
  <li>‘n’ to not stage this hunk</li>
  <li>’s’ to split this hunk</li>
  <li>‘q’ to quit; do not stage this hunk or any of the remaining ones</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="best-practices" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[partial file staging]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sample Return from all across the Solar System (KISS workshop)</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/kiss-workshop/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sample Return from all across the Solar System (KISS workshop)" /><published>2024-09-09T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/kiss-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/kiss-workshop/"><![CDATA[<p>I was fortunate to be invited to this <a href="https://kiss.caltech.edu/short_courses/sample_return.html">short course</a> organized by the Keck Institute of Space Studies called “Sample Return from all across the Solar System”.
This experience offered me a great opportunity to learn more about the science behind sample return missions and the challenges faced by the scientists and engineers involved in these missions.
As an engineer, I’m keen to bridge the gap between engineering and the scientific principles underlying different missions.</p>

<p>This course also resonated with a question that deeply interests me: “Where and how can we discover life within the Solar System and beyond?”</p>

<p>Here’s a brief summary of what I’ve learned:</p>

<h4 id="talk-1-past-sample-return-missions-and-major-achievements-by-m-zolensky-nasa-johnson-space-center"><strong>Talk 1.</strong> Past Sample Return Missions and Major Achievements, by M. Zolensky, NASA Johnson Space Center</h4>

<p>He gave examples of sample return missions from the Moon:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Samples from Lunar Near Side: Luna, Apollo, Chang’e missions</li>
  <li>Samples from Lunar Far Side: Chang’e</li>
</ul>

<p>and talked about some major unanswered questions, such as the nature and amount of water at the south pole, details about the bombardment history, and possible involvement with early life emergence on Earth.</p>

<p>Then, the Genesis mission (figure below) was presented, which was launched in August 2001 to collect solar wind samples and return them to Earth. Some of the major results of this mission include the measurement of O isotope abundances.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-09-09/genesis.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="genesis" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>Then, he talked about some experiments that were conducted to collect astroid and comet dust, such as the Long Duration Exposure Facility (figure below). “The Long Duration Exposure Facility, or LDEF, was a cylindrical facility designed to provide long-term experimental data on the outer space environment and its effects on space systems, materials, operations and selected spores’ survival.” It was placed in Low Earth Orbit by the Space Shuttle Challenger in 1984 and was retrieved by the Space Shuttle Columbia in 1990. (source: Wikipedia).
There were also some experiments conducted on the ISS, such as the Tanpopo experiments, which used silica gel to collect micrometeorites.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-09-09/ldef.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="ldef" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<!-- Requirements of these samples drove great advances in analytical techniques. -->

<!-- Asteroids are separated in terms of reflectance spectrum. -->
<p>Some examples of astroid sample return missions include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Hayabusa recovered &lt; 1g material</li>
  <li>Hayabusa2 recovered 5.4 grams</li>
  <li>OSIRIS-REx recovered 121 grams</li>
</ul>

<p>Kind of crazy to think how little material was recovered from these missions, but how much we can learn from them. And one important thing to note is that the samples must be returned in a vacuum, as they are extremely reactive to everything on Earth.</p>

<p>Some examples of comet sample return missions include:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Stardust: 81P/Wild 2</li>
  <li>Rosetta from 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko</li>
</ul>

<p>I also learnt that the “P” in 67P stands for Period comet.</p>

<p>Some other lessons learned: samples must be returned in an airtight container. Hhe health and safety should be 
the primary mission priority, sample analysis techniques continue to evolve, team membership should be very inclusive and flexible and samples will be extremely reactive to everything on Earth.</p>

<p>I really love learning about all the different space missions and the science behind them. When I was in high school, I had this challenge with myself to learn by heart all the different NASA missions to date.</p>

<h4 id="talk-2-linking-the-protosolar-disk-with-the-inner-solar-system-by-prof-françois-tissot"><strong>Talk 2</strong> “Linking the protosolar disk with the inner Solar System”, by Prof. François Tissot.</h4>

<p>He started by presenting the different types of meteorites:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Stony meteorites, from crusts/mantles</li>
  <li>Iron meteortites, from cores</li>
  <li>Stony-iron meteorites</li>
  <li>Chondrites (figure below)</li>
</ul>

<p>He talked about isotope anomalies.
There were quite some details that were hard to follow for me, because I am not a geologist,
but I got the general idea. Maybe I should do a 3rd Masters in geology.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-09-09/meteorite.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="meteorite" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>He also mentioned that Venus return missions are very important.
I also learned about the chrondritic model, which models the composition of Earth. Scientists are arguing whether this model is correct or not.
Also, that isotopic anomalies are very important for understanding the formation of the solar system.</p>

<h4 id="talk-3-dynamical-evolution-by-prof-karen-meech"><strong>Talk 3</strong> “Dynamical Evolution” by Prof. Karen Meech</h4>

<p>I really wish I would have attended this talk, but I had to attend another meeting at that time. I will try to find the recording and watch it.</p>

<h4 id="talk-4-ocean-worlds-and-habitability-by-prof-jonathan-lunine"><strong>Talk 4</strong> Ocean Worlds and Habitability, by Prof. Jonathan Lunine</h4>

<p>Some of the facts I learned from the talk are below:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Oceanworld are bodies with substantial liquid water on their surfaces or within their interiors. They are very interesting for astrobiology.</li>
  <li>Habitability requires that three or four general conditions be met: energy, appropriate physical and chemical conditions, solvent, and elemental requirements.</li>
  <li>Conditions for abiogenesis is still a mystery (habitability bottleneck).</li>
  <li>Types of measurements to require habilitability: geophysical, chemical, isotopic, and electromagnetic.</li>
  <li>The oceans of Europa were discovered by a magnetometer on Galileo.</li>
</ul>

<p>Saturn’s moon Enceladus (figure below) is one of the easiest to explore. There is evidence of an ocean. 
There are organics in the Enceladus ocean, but their identity is not known.
There is evidence there is redox chemistry in the ocean of Enceladus.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-09-09/enceladus.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="enceladus" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>

<p>Europa Clipper will orbit Jupiter and make 50 fly-bys of Europa. 
For ocean worlds, present-day habitability can be established by in-situ measurements.</p>

<p>I liked that he presented both pros and cons for sample return missions.</p>

<h4 id="talk-5---ices-in-the-outer-solar-system-and-their-connection-to-the-protoplanetary-disk-by-prof-mike-brown"><strong>Talk 5</strong> - Ices in the Outer Solar System and their Connection to the Protoplanetary Disk, by Prof. Mike Brown</h4>

<p>I didn’t know, but during the early solar system, the planets were closer together.
He also showed and explained us plots of reflectance spectra (reflectance vs. wavelength), which was very interesting to see.</p>

<p>I also realized I wish I would know more about chemistry.</p>

<hr />

<p>Source of the images: The internet</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="astroids" /><category term="comets" /><category term="moon" /><category term="keck-institute-of-space-studies" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sample return missions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ankle actuators</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/ankle-torques/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ankle actuators" /><published>2024-07-29T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-29T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/ankle-torques</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/ankle-torques/"><![CDATA[<p>I initially designed the robot without actuated ankles, planning to add ankle torques once the robot achieved walking.
However, the initial design required the robot to step quickly, making testing by myself extremely challenging.
Now, it’s time to invest in designing the actuated ankles.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="design">Design</h3>

<p>I consider three options:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>motor + low gear ratio (cable-driven)</strong>
<br /> 👍: It is a compact design
<br /> 👎:  Less experience designing this. The cable needs to not stretch over time.</li>
  <li><strong>motor + low gear ratio (belt-driven)</strong>
<br /> 👍: experience designing belt-driven actuators, as I’ve already designed some for the knee and yaw joints.
<br /> 👎: It might be too bulky/heavy</li>
  <li><strong>series elastic actuators</strong>
<br />  👍: Can absorb impacts better
<br />  👎: Less experience designing this. I need to find a way to measure the spring deflection.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h3 id="controls">Controls</h3>

<p>For the control, I would like to employ a straightforward feedback law. I’m not trying at this point to do something very complicated, because I want to get the robot to walk first.
So I want something along the lines of 
\(u = - k_p x_{zmp} - k_d v,\)
 where zmp stands for zero moment point.
 Initially, I was thinking to use the velocity of the zmp. However, I believe that signal will be too noisy.
So I can use the ankle velocity computed geometrically as the robot moves forward.</p>

<hr />

<p>I decided to go with the series elastic actuators, so I’ll document the sizing, manufacturing, and testing in a separate blog post.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="robotics" /><category term="biped" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to design ankles that are actuated]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">loose connectors</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/connectors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="loose connectors" /><published>2024-07-24T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/connectors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/connectors/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the main challenges I’ve faced with connectors for my biped’s motors is preventing them from being under excessive tension.
As the robot moves its legs, significant mechanical stress can be applied to these connectors, and if this stress is not properly managed, the connectors can become loose over time.</p>

<p>To illustrate this, I have two GIFs: one showing a connector without proper mechanical stress relief and one where the stress relief was implemented properly.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-07-24/IMG_0658.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="loose connection" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-07-24/IMG_0664.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="tight connection" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Loose connection vs. tight connection for the XT30 connector on the MJBots motor controller.
</div>

<p>One issue arising from unstable power supplies is the potential for voltage drops or spikes on the CANbus.
This can lead to many problems, including motor drivers breaking.
For example, one of my MJBots motor driver recently signaled Fault 33, indicating a likely malfunction.
According to the <a href="https://github.com/mjbots/moteus/blob/main/docs/reference.md">documentation</a>, it means: “the most common reason for this is undervoltage, moteus attempted to draw more current than the supply could provide.”
MJBots provides really nice tech support on their Discord channels, so according to them: “That indicates damage to the gate driver or fets or both”. I ordered a new motor driver, which just arrived, so I’ll solder it real quick.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, I’ve asked one of my summer students, Cesar, to design a mount to be able to attach the cables more securely.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-07-24/mounts.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="mounts" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="robotics" /><category term="electrical_engineering" /><category term="biped" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[connectors]]></summary></entry></feed>