<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2024-08-18T03:09:39+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>website
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ankle actuators</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/ankle-torques/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ankle actuators" /><published>2024-07-29T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-29T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/ankle-torques</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/ankle-torques/"><![CDATA[<p>I initially designed the robot without actuated ankles, planning to add ankle torques once the robot achieved walking.
However, the initial design required the robot to step quickly, making testing by myself extremely challenging.
Now, it’s time to invest in designing the actuated ankles.”</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="design">Design</h3>

<p>I consider three options:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>motor + low gear ratio (cable-driven)</strong>
<br /> 👍: It is a compact design
<br /> 👎:  Less experience designing this. The cable needs to not stretch over time.</li>
  <li><strong>motor + low gear ratio (belt-driven)</strong>
<br /> 👍: experience designing belt-driven actuators, as I’ve already designed some for the knee and yaw joints.
<br /> 👎: It might be too bulky/heavy</li>
  <li><strong>series elastic actuators</strong>
<br />  👍: Can absorb impacts better
<br />  👎: Less experience designing this. I need to find a way to measure the spring deflection.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<h3 id="controls">Controls</h3>

<p>For the control, I would like to employ a straightforward feedback law. I’m not trying at this point to do something very complicated, because I want to get the robot to walk first.
So I want something along the lines of 
\(u = - k_p x_{zmp} - k_d v,\)
 where zmp stands for zero moment point.
 Initially, I was thinking to use the velocity of the zmp. However, I believe that signal will be too noisy.
So I can use the ankle velocity computed geometrically as the robot moves forward.</p>

<hr />

<p>I decided to go with the series elastic actuators, so I’ll document the sizing, manufacturing, and testing in a separate blog post.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="robotics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How to design ankles that are actuated]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">loose connectors</title><link href="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/connectors/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="loose connectors" /><published>2024-07-24T13:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-24T13:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/connectors</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://lupusorina.github.io/blog/2024/connectors/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the main challenges I’ve faced with connectors for my biped’s motors is preventing them from being under excessive tension.
As the robot moves its legs, significant mechanical stress can be applied to these connectors, and if this stress is not properly managed, the connectors can become loose over time.</p>

<p>To illustrate this, I have two GIFs: one showing a connector without proper mechanical stress relief and one where the stress relief was implemented properly.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-07-24/IMG_0658.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="loose connection" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
    <div class="col-sm-3 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-07-24/IMG_0664.mp4" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="tight connection" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>
<div class="caption">
Loose connection vs. tight connection for the XT30 connector on the MJBots motor controller.
</div>

<p>One issue arising from unstable power supplies is the potential for voltage drops or spikes on the CANbus.
This can lead to many problems, including motor drivers breaking.
For example, one of my MJBots motor driver recently signaled Fault 33, indicating a likely malfunction.
According to the <a href="https://github.com/mjbots/moteus/blob/main/docs/reference.md">documentation</a>, it means: “the most common reason for this is undervoltage, moteus attempted to draw more current than the supply could provide.”
MJBots provides really nice tech support on their Discord channels, so according to them: “That indicates damage to the gate driver or fets or both”. I ordered a new motor driver, which just arrived, so I’ll solder it real quick.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, I’ve asked one of my summer students, Cesar, to design a mount to be able to attach the cables more securely.</p>

<div class="row justify-content-sm-center">
    <div class="col-sm-6 mt-3 mt-md-0">
        <figure>

  <picture>
    

    <!-- Fallback to the original file -->
    <img src="/assets/img/2024-07-24/mounts.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" title="mounts" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();" />

  </picture>

</figure>

    </div>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts" /><category term="robotics" /><category term="electrical_engineering" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[connectors]]></summary></entry></feed>